<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Maíra Canal</title>
        <description>Blogging about graphics development whenever I can</description>
        <link>https://mairacanal.github.io</link>
        <atom:link href="https://mairacanal.github.io/atom-life.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        <lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
        
            <item>
                <title>Talking to Neurotypicals</title>
                
                <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m neurodivergent (ND). I found out when I was 19 and one day, I can tell a bit
about how I was diagnosed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I was diagnosed by 19, definitely, I was born like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I found out, my whole life made sense. I always thought I was a bit odd
compared to the other kids. But I never really understood why.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I always had very specific topics that I’d love to talk about. And the topics
can be pretty broad. I can talk for hours about the Sega vs. Nintendo 90s war
or maybe talk about the impacts of tranquilizers advertising for housewives
in the 60s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Currently, my hyperfocus is fixated on Kubrick’s movies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I do love to be an ND person. Especially, when I found other ND people
that I can flood my hyperfocus on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But being an ND person in a neurotypical (NT) world can be quite challenging.
And I would like to start this series with my personal biggest challenge:
talking to NT people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually, ND people have a very pragmatic way of communicating. We tend to be
more direct and say exactly what we mean. NT has a way - that really drives
me mad - to say things in a kind of doublespeak.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some cultures, our blunt and direct communication style can be seen as rude.
But on the other hand, sometimes we cannot really understand what neurotypical
wants from us with that dubious communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember when I used to review code when I was in
&lt;a href=&quot;https://zenith.eesc.usp.br/en&quot;&gt;Zenith Aerospace&lt;/a&gt;. I used to be really direct
about the defects in the code, making comments like, “I’m not sure how this even
works. This can clearly lead to UB.” One day, a good NT friend told me how hurt
people could get by my comments in the code and it could disengage them from
coding. For me, I was just saying “This is broken, fix it.” But in the neurotypical
world, this is not how it works. Then, I learned about the fabulous world of
non-aggressive communication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, when I review code, I try to be assertive, but not rude to the person.
I learned that it is nice to compliment your partner’s work before asking for changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;the-bridge&quot;&gt;The Bridge&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s on NT people, as much as it is ND people, to bridge the communication gap.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More often than not, NT people put the responsibility on ND individuals to adapt
and conform to NT expectations of communication, which can be harmful and
counterproductive to the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These expectations can hurt ND people trying to land a job or keep their jobs.
Gladly, I work in an ND-friendly company (BTW I work at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.igalia.com/&quot;&gt;Igalia&lt;/a&gt;),
but not every ND individual is as fortunate as I am. Most of these folks, who
are ND and communicate in ways that NTs might find a bit different, have stories
about how they’ve had a tough time landing a job, holding onto one, or moving up
in their careers because people tend to think that without those so-called
“essential skills,” they won’t be as good at what they do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I gathered some tips to bridge this NT/ND communication gap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer:&lt;/strong&gt; These tips are based on my personal experience and some years
of psychotherapy. I’m not a mental health professional. I’m just an ND open-source developer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;im-neurotypical-what-should-i-do&quot;&gt;I’m neurotypical. What should I do?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first tip to talk to an ND person is to &lt;strong&gt;communicate clearly and unambiguously&lt;/strong&gt;.
Yeah, this doesn’t mean the same for everyone, but you can’t go wrong with
keeping your language free of euphemisms, sarcasm, and vagueness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I always say to my coworkers that they can communicate with me as
directly as possible. This makes it easier for me to understand what they want
from me. It’s pretty difficult to be to handle broad tasks. I need some scope to
work on. But this is my functional style. Different ND people have different styles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an NT person, you can ask your ND coworkers if you are being clear enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, we need to be mindful of the environment, as background noise and other
sensory input can make it more difficult for ND people to process what is being said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that I can surely recommend to everyone (ND or NT) is learning about
assertive communication. Assertive communication is a style of expressing oneself
that involves confidently stating thoughts, feelings, and needs while respecting
the rights and opinions of others. In assertive communication, individuals
communicate their ideas clearly and directly without being aggressive or overly
passive. It involves expressing opinions, setting boundaries, and standing up
for oneself calmly and respectfully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, an important aspect to consider is that ND people can go through
different states in a single day. This means that we can have tons of energy in
the morning and then, feel completely overwhelmed in the afternoon. Maybe we are
in some sort of hyperfocus about tax deduction in Brazil (yeah, true story).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;im-neurodivergent-what-should-i-do&quot;&gt;I’m neurodivergent. What should I do?&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My go-to tip is to &lt;strong&gt;ask&lt;/strong&gt;! I used to be shy, and my NT coworkers would say
things to me that I didn’t really understand. But instead of asking what
they mean, I would stay in doubt and get frustrated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best thing I learned was to ask questions. Also, inform my coworkers
about my communication style. Then, they can be more assertive with me and
the communication flows more easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until this point, I never got any negative feedback from asking questions
or telling my coworkers that “I’m an ND person, and if possible I would like
you to be as clear as possible.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Okay, I work in this super awesome company, but I’m pretty sure that no NT
will take it in a negative way to ask what they mean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;im-neurodivergent-but-i-dont-feel-comfortable-disclosing-this-information-to-my-employer&quot;&gt;I’m neurodivergent, but I don’t feel comfortable disclosing this information to my employer&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just a small group of ND workers feel okay talking about their neurodivergence
at work. In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.talentinnovation.org/_private/assets/DisabilitiesInclusion_KeyFindings-CTI.pdf&quot;&gt;2017 report&lt;/a&gt;,
it said that “about 30% of college-educated folks working office jobs had some
kind of disability,” but only 3.2% actually told their bosses about it. And this
isn’t just about the invisible disabilities that come with being ND
(and surely, not everyone with ND thinks of themselves as disabled).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gladly, I work in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.igalia.com/&quot;&gt;Igalia&lt;/a&gt;. So, I felt pretty free to
disclose that I’ve been an ND person ever since my job interview.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, if you don’t feel free to disclose to your employer about being
neurodivergent, you can try assertive communication with your
coworkers. I’m pretty sure this can help you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;a-final-word&quot;&gt;A Final Word&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never introduced myself as an ND person. Usually, I only mention this fact
after a couple of contact with the person. I still fear the repercussions this
information could have in my life. We never know who is listening to this
information. We never know what they could be thinking about us. What sort of
ideas do they have about what is a ND person? Does this person believe that an
ND person is a disabled person?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a great talk to my mentor, I realized I should be more proud of my ND.
It’s part of who I am, and I can try to help our community be more friendly
to ND people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe we can start to close this communiction gap in our community.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
                <pubDate>Fri, 09 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
                <link>https://mairacanal.github.io/life/talking-to-neurotypicals/</link>
                <guid isPermaLink="true">https://mairacanal.github.io/life/talking-to-neurotypicals/</guid>
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
